Guide to the Millen Brand Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Millen Brand Papers
1919-1976.
Brand, Millen, 1906-1980.
40 linear ft (ca. 40,000 items in 95 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0145
4079473
This collection contains correspondence, journals, manuscripts, documents, memorabilia, and printed materials relating to writer Millen Brand.
Biographical Note
Author, poet, Hollywood screenwriter, editor at Crown Publishers, Inc., teacher of writing at New York University. Brand was active in the Left during the 1930s and in the Civil Rights movement.
Scope and Content
Personal and literary correspondence, journals from 1919 to 1976, manuscripts of Brand's novels, poems, articles and other writings, documents, memorabilia, and printed materials. Novels by Brand include THE OUTWARD ROOM (1937), a novel about mental illness; THE HEROES (1939), a novel about veterans' hospitals; ALBERT SEARS (1947), a novel about racial intolerance; THE SNAKE PIT (1948), a screenplay about mental illness, SOME LOVE, SOME HUNGER (1955), a novel about Puerto Ricans in New York; SAVAGE SLEEP (1965), a novel about the use of shock treatment; DRY SUMMER IN PROVENCE (1966), poems about the South of France; FIELDS OF PEACE (1970), poems; LOCAL LIVES (1975), poems about Mennonites of Pennsylvania; and PEACE MARCH (1980), poems. Correspondents include Nancy Cunard, Lion Feuchtwanger, Ernest Hemingway, Rockwell Kent, Harriet Monroe, Joyce Carol Oates, Kenneth Patchen, Diego Rivera, Jules Romains, May Sarton, Louis Untermeyer, Thornton Wilder, Colin Wilson, and Darryl F. Zanuck.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Catalogued Correspondence
Series II: Uncatalogued Correspondence
Series III: Papers
Subjects
Cunard, Nancy, 1896-1965.; Feuchtwanger, Lion, 1884-1958.; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Monroe, Harriet, 1860-1936.; Oates, Joyce Carol, 1938-; Patchen, Kenneth, 1911-1972.; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957.; Romains, Jules, 1885-1972.; Sarton, May, 1912-1995.; Untermeyer, Louis, 1885-1977.; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975.; Wilson, Colin, 1894-; Zanuck, Darryl Francis, 1902-1979.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1953.; English language--Study and teaching.; College teachers--New York (State)--New York--Political activity.; Civil rights--United States.; Journals.; Poems.; College teachers.; Poets, American.; Authors, American.; Editors.; Screenwriters.
Acquisition
1954 M-54 Brand, Millen Gift
1961 M-1961 Brand letters to Lillian Gilkes Gilkes, Lillian Gift
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 1-89. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Alternate Formats
William Goyen letters are on microfilm.
Gift of Millen Brand, 1954-1976.
Gift of Lillian Gilkes, 1961.
- Series I: Catalogued Correspondence
  - A-D
    - Abbe, George Bancroft (Box A)
    - Alajalov, Constantin (Box A)
    - Algren, Nelson (Box A)
    - Anderson, Eleanor C. (Mrs Sherwood) (Box A)
    - Anderson, Margaret (Box A)
    - Anthony, Katharine Susan (Box A)
    - Baldwin, Faith (Box A)
    - Bazin, Herve (Box A)
    - Benoit-Levy, Jean (Box A)
    - Bernstein, Aline Frankau (Box A)
    - Bessie, Alvah Cecil (Box A)
    - Bishop, Jim (Box A)
    - Bliven^ Bruce (Box A)
    - Bourjaily, Vance (Box A)
    - Boyle, Kay (Box A)
    - Brewster, Dorothy (Box A)
    - Brown, Leonard (Box A)
    - Budenz, Louis Francis (Box A)
    - Bukowski, Charles (Box A)
    - Burke, Kenneth Duva (Box A)
    - Burnett, Whit (Box A)
    - Butcher, Fanny (Box A)
    - Bynner, Witter (Box A)
    - Caidwell, Erskine (Box A)
    - Calisher, Hortense (Box A)
    - Cardona-Hine, Alvaro (Box A)
    - Carruth, Hayden (Box A)
    - Christowe, Stoyan (Box A)
    - Chute, Marchette Gaylord (Box A)
    - Ciardi, John (Box A)
    - Cohen, Abbot S. (Box A)
    - Conroy, Jack (Box A)
    - Cooper, Gladys (Box A)
    - Corey, Paul (Box A)
    - Cournos, John (Box A)
    - Cowley, Malcolm (Box A)
    - Cunard, Nancy Clara (Box A)
    - Davidson, Jo (Box A)
    - Davis, Harry (Box A)
    - de Havilland, Olivia Mary (Box A)
    - DeJong, David Cornel (Box A)
    - Deutsch, Babette (Box A)
    - De Vries, Peter (Box A)
    - Du Bois, William Edward Burghardt (Box A)
    - Du Von, Jay (Box A)
  - E-K
    - Endore, Guy (Box B)
    - Fast, Howard (Box B)
    - Fearing, Kenneth (Box B)
    - Feuchtwanger, Lion (Box B)
    - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield (Box B)
    - Fitts, Dudley (Box B)
    - Foley, Martha (Box B)
    - Frank, Waldo David (Box B)
    - Geismar, Maxwell (Box B)
    - Goyen, William (Box B)
    - Gregory, Horace Victor (Box B)
    - Hammett, Dashiell (Box B)
    - Hansen, Harry (Box B)
    - Harrison, Jay (Box B)
    - Hellman, Lillian (Box B)
    - Hemingway, Ernest (Box B)
    - Hentoff, Nathan Irving (Box B)
    - Herlihy, James Leo (Box B)
    - Hersholt, Jean (Box B)
    - Hodnett, Edward (Box B)
    - Hoffman, Malvina (Box B)
    - Holmes, John (Box B)
    - Hughes, Langston (Box B)
    - Humphries, Rolfe (Box B)
    - Javits, Jacob Koppel (Box B)
    - Johns, Orrick (Box B)
    - Johns, Richard (Box B)
    - Kent, Rockwell (Box B)
    - Kerr, Harrison (Box B)
    - Kingsley, Sidney (Box B)
    - Knight, Eric (Box B)
    - Koch, Edward I. (Box B)
    - Komroff, Manuel (Box B)
    - Kozlenko, William (Box B)
    - Kreymborg, Alfred (Box B)
    - Kuhlman, Fred (Box B)
    - Kunitz, Joshua (Box B)
    - Kunitz, Stanley J. et al. (Box B)
  - L
    - La Farge, Oliver Hazard Perry (Box C)
    - Lamont, Corliss (Box C)
    - Latham, Harold Strong (Box C)
    - Laurents, Arthur (Box C)
    - Leach, Henry Goddard (Box C)
    - Levertov, Denise (Box C)
    - Lindsay, Howard (Box C)
    - Lowenstein-Wertheim-Freudenberg, Hubertus zu (Box C)
    - Loveman, Amy (Box C)
    - Lowenfels, Lillian Apotheker (Mrs Walter) (Box C)
    - Lowenfels, Walter (Box C)
  - M-R
    - McCarthy, Joseph Raymond (Box D)
    - McConnell, Francis John (Box D)
    - McGrath, Thomas (Box D)
    - Macleod, Norman Wicklund (Box D)
    - McWilliams, Carey (Box D)
    - Maltz, Albert (Box D)
    - Manch, Joseph Rodman (Box D)
    - Mangione, Jerre Gerlando (Box D)
    - Menninger, Karl August (Box D)
    - Meredith, Burgess (Box D)
    - Merriam, Harold G. (Box D)
    - Monroe, Harriet (Box D)
    - Moore, Marianne Craig (Box D)
    - Nearing, Scott & Helen K. Nearing (Box D)
    - Neel, Alice (Box D)
    - Norman, Dorothy Stecher (Box D)
    - Oates, Joyce Carol (Box D)
    - Orlovitz, Gil (Box D)
    - Paley, Grace Goodside (Box D)
    - Patchen, Kenneth (Box D)
    - Paul, Elliot Harold (Box D)
    - Percy, Charles Harting (Box D)
    - Pittala, Berenice (Box D)
    - Prescott, Orville (Box D)
    - Quinn, Kerker (Box D)
    - Quintanilla, Luis (Box D)
    - Randall, Margaret (Box D)
    - Rexroth, Kenneth (Box D)
    - Rice, Elmer L. et al. (Box D)
    - Rivera, Diego (Box D)
    - Romains, Jules (Box D)
    - Rood, John (Box D)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor Roosevelt (Box D)
    - Rosten, Norman (Box D)
    - Rushmore, Howard (Box D)
    - Rustin, Bayard (Box D)
  - S-V
    - Sandoz, Marl Susette (Box E)
    - Sarton, May (Box E)
    - Savage, Augusta (Box E)
    - Schneider, Isidor (Box E)
    - Schuster, Max Lincoln (Box E)
    - Seaver, Edwin (Box E)
    - Shapiro, Karl (Box E)
    - Shearer, Norma (Box E)
    - Sherby, John M. (Box E)
    - Simon, Richard Leo (Box E)
    - Soyer, Moses (Box E)
    - Soyer, Raphael (Box E)
    - Stafford, Jean (Box E)
    - Stead, Christina Ellen (Box E)
    - Steig, William (Box E)
    - Stern, Philip Van Doren (Box E)
    - Stoll, J. Louis (Box E)
    - Stout, Rex Todhunter (Box E)
    - Thomas, Lowell (Box E)
    - Thompson, Ralph (Box E)
    - Tully, Jim (Box E)
    - Untermeyer, Louis (Box E)
    - Van Doren, Mark (Box E)
    - Voorhis, Jerry (Box E)
  - W-Z
    - Webb, Jon Edgar (Box F)
    - Weidman, Jerome (Box F)
    - Wexley, John (Box F)
    - Wheelock, John Hall (Box F)
    - Wilder, Thornton Niven (Box F)
    - Wilhelm, Gale (Box F)
    - Williams, Jonathan (Box F)
    - Wilson, Colin Henry (Box F)
    - Winter, Ella (Box F)
    - Wirth, Nicholas (Box F)
    - Woodman, Lawrence C. (Box F)
    - Wright, Richard (Box F)
    - Young, Agatha (Box F)
    - Zabel, Morton Dauwen (Box F)
    - Zanuck, Darryl Francis (Box F)
    - Zara, Louis (Box F)
- Series II: Uncatalogued Correspondence
  - 1929-1938 (& older copies) (Box 1)
  - 1937-1940 (Box 2)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - 1941-1943 (Box 5)
  - 1943-1945 (Box 6)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 7)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 8)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 9)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 10)
  - 1952 (Box 11)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 12)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 13)
  - 1956 (Box 14)
  - 1957 (Box 15)
  - 1958 (Box 16)
  - 1959 (Box 17)
  - 1960 (Box 18)
  - 1961 (Box 19)
  - 1962 (Box 20)
  - 1963 (Box 21)
  - 1964 (Box 22)
  - 1965 (Box 23)
  - 1966 (Box 24)
  - 1967 (Box 25)
  - 1968 (Box 26)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 27)
  - 1969 (Box 28)
  - 1970 (Box 29-30)
  - 1971 (Box 31)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 32)
  - 1972 (Box 33)
  - 1973 (Box 34)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 35)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 36)
  - 1975 (Box 37)
  - 1976 (Box 38)
  - Crown Publishers, Inc. (1963-1975)
    - A-Bo (Box 39)
    - Br-E (Box 40)
    - F-K (Box 41)
    - Maj-P (Box 42)
    - R-S (Box 43)
    - Tait, Dorothy (Box 44)
    - T-Y (Box 45)
    - Series III: Papers
      - Manuscripts
        - Novels
          - Albert Sears (drafts) (Box 46-47)
            - copy-edited draft, Galley proofs, outline, reviews, source materials, etc. (Box 48)
          - The Great Summer, The Heroes, Laura, The Outward Room, Seven Times Waking (Box 49)
          - Savage Sleep (drafts, etc.) (Box 50-53)
          - Some Love, Some Hunger (drafts) (Box 54-56)
            - [Discarded drafts in Box 56] (Box 56)
        - Poems
          - Dry Summer in Provence (Box 57)
          - Local Lives (drafts) (Box 58-66)
            - [Contents & notes in Box 58] (Box 58)
          - Individual Poems & early drafts (Box 67-70)
        - Short Stories
          - A-M (Box 71)
          - N-Y (Box 72)
        - Textbook
          - How to write one story (Box 73)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Articles, Book reviews, Copywriting, Drawings & watercolors, Lecture notes, Notes, Playscript, Radio Interviews, Screenplays (Box 74)
          - Screenplays, Manuscripts edited or translated by Brand or with his preface and jacket copy, etc. (Box 75)
      - Journal
        - 1919-1943 (Box 76)
        - 1944-1955 (Box 77)
        - 1955-1956 (Box 78)
        - 1957-1960 (Box 79)
        - 1961-1965 (Box 80)
        - 1965-1967 (Box 81)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 82)
        - 1970-1972 (Box 83)
        - 1972-1973 (Box 84)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 85)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 86)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Photographs, Pennsylvania land deeds (1914-1930) (Box 87)
        - Printed books by Millen Brand, Printed Misc. (Box 88)
        - Periodicals with contributions by Brand (Box 89)